（ひなた）お姉ちゃん　大丈夫
It'll be all right.
ありがとう　ひなは頑張るから
Thank you.
I'm going to hang in there.
Thank you, Sis.
ありがとう お姉ちゃん
Sorry for interrupting.
（国分(こくぶ)）失礼しますよ
（ひなた）あっ 先生
Oh, Mr. Kokubu.
How are you feeling?
（国分）
お姉さん　具合は いかがですか？
I'm really sorry.
（あかり）すみません 先生
あの…　もう大丈夫ですので
Um, I feel better now, so—
（国分）
ああ ああ…　そのまま そのまま
It's okay. No need to get up.
（あかり）あの…　先生
Uh, Mr. Kokubu, I was being quite rude earlier...
先ほどは私 大変 失礼を…　その…
Um...
You have nothing at all to be sorry about.
（国分）ああ お姉さん　何も何も
気にすることなんて何もないです
It's okay.
大丈夫　それより…
More importantly...
さあ　これからの話をしましょうか
Well then,
why don't we discuss our next steps?
Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
A Small Palm
Hey, Mr. Kokubu.
（高城(たかぎ)）ねえ 先生
How long are you gonna keep calling me here?
（高城）私 いつまで
呼び出されるんですか？
I mean...
…ていうか
謝りましたよね？
I already apologized.
Right?
もう
（国分）ああ　口ではな
Yes. With your words.
I'm sorry for what I did.
（高城）
どうも〜 すみませんでした
I apologized, and I'm keeping my mouth shut in class.
（高城）ちゃんと謝ったし
おとなしくしてるのだから—
Isn't that enough?
もういいでしょう？
Part of the work is becoming aware of what you did.
何をしたか自覚してもらうのも
仕事のうちだからな
What'll happen if I become aware of it?
（高城）自覚したら どうなるの？
何か変わるの？
Will something change?
If something changes, will I get something good out of it?
変わったら 何か いいことあるの？
ねえ 先生
Tell me, Mr. Kokubu.
Will something good happen if we keep living?
私たち この先 生きてて
何かいいことあんの？
（高城）
お母さんも お父さんも みんな
My parents and everyone around me say do your best
and study hard so you can get into a good high school,
頑張って勉強して いい学校
行かないとダメだって言うけど—
but even if I got into a good school, who's to say I'll get a job at all, let alone one at a good company?
いい学校に入っても
いい会社どころか—
今は就職できるかも
分かんないんでしょう？
"If you do your best, you'll get good results."
“頑張れば
いいことある”って—
There's no guarantee of that,
yet people still say, "Do your best!"
保証もないくせに
“頑張れ 頑張れ”って
Isn't that crazy?
それ おかしくない？
It's like, if I worked as hard as I could, but it didn't work out, nobody's going to take responsibility.
一生懸命 頑張ったあげくに
ダメだったとしても—
誰も
責任取ってくれないんでしょう？
（国分）う〜ん そうか…
I see.
それで お前は
“将来が不安だった”と
So you're anxious about the future because of that.
And your parents don't understand you.
“両親が
自分のこと分かってくれない”と
I see, I see.
ふむふむ …で？
So?
What part of that has anything to do with Kawamoto and Sakura?
それの どこら辺が
川本(かわもと)と佐倉(さくら)に関係あんの？
It's totally unrelated, right?
全然 関係ないよね
Stop talking like you've come to the
conclusion that it's all society's fault.
そうやって 全部
世の中の空気のせいみたいに—
まとめんの やめてね
Keep it up and I'll start talking about life in Japan when I was a kid.
そんなん言ってると
俺 昭和(しょうわ)20年代の話 始めるよ
The postwar period!
戦後だぞ　まだ戦後！
It was still postwar times!
If I did that, you'd be like,
"That has nothing to do with this." Sheesh!
そうすっと お前ら—
“あ〜 そんなこと
今言われても関係ないし”とか—
言うんだろう？　…たく
（高城）先生には
私の気持ちなんて分かんないよ
You wouldn't understand how I feel.
（国分）
うん　だから 今聞いてるんだよ
That's why I'm asking now!
話そうぜ
Let's talk!
（ひなた）
さてと…　シソは これでよし
All right.
The perilla plant is set.
（あかり）
バジルは その横でいいよ
We can put the basil next to it.
And let's put the mint somewhere else.
…で ミントは別にしよう
増え過ぎるからね
It likes to grow wild.
Right.
Now let's give them plenty of water.
（あかり）
水あげよっか　たっぷりめにね
Okay.
Last week in homeroom,
Mr. Kokubu said something to the class with a clear voice.
（ひなた）
先週 ホームルームの時間に—
先生が よく通る声で言った
（国分）
さてと…　今日は みんなに—
Okay, today there are several things I want to ask you.
ちょっと いろいろ
聞かせてほしいことがあるんだ
First of all, Arai, Takashi, Kimura,
Mochizuki, Takagi, and Wakabayashi.
…で まず 荒井(あらい) 高師(たかし) 木村(きむら)
持月(もちづき) 高城 若林(わかばやし)
There are individual questions for you six,
so you'll each go with a teacher to another classroom.
この６人は
個別に質問があるんで—
それぞれの先生について
ほかの教室へ
That's when everyone in the class realized.
（ひなた）
ここで クラス全員が気がついた
The school had gotten serious about
intervening in the darkness in our class.
クラスの中の闇に
学校側が本気で介入してきたことに
Now we knew this teacher wasn't just going through the motions of doing something.
この先生は 決して これを—
うやむやにする気は
ないということに
（国分）さてと…
Okay.
I guess we'll get started here.
じゃ ざっくりといこうかね
…で！
So...
tell me what's really going on.
ぶっちゃけ どうなの？
実際のとこ
（ひなた）クラスの中に
流れていた暗黙のルールが—
The unwritten rules that had spread in our class wouldn't work anymore.
ここからは通用しなくなること
Everyone realized that maybe the days of living in
fear of becoming the next target may now be over.
もう “次のターゲットは
自分かも”と—
おびえて過ごす日々は
終わるのかもしれないということ
And so, the curtain dropped.
（ひなた）そして 幕は閉じたのだ
Um, I apologize.
え〜っと…　すみませんでした
I'm sorry.
（高師たち）
すみません　ごめんなさい
And with it came words that made it hard to tell if it was really over at all.
（ひなた）閉じたのかどうかも
分からない言葉で…
There wasn't one bit of sincerity in that.
心 みじんも籠もってねえし
まだ先は長そうだな
It seems we've still got a long way to go.
先生
私 許さなくてもいいですか？
Mr. Kokubu, is it okay if I don't forgive them?
Just say, "apologize and you'll be forgiven," with no punishment given.
何の罰則もなくて “謝ったら
許される”くらいのことで—
When I think about how Chiho had to change schools,
ちほちゃんは
転校しなきゃいけなかったなんて…
そんなの やりきれないから
it's too much to forgive.
"Compassion"?
（高城）思いやり？
う〜ん…
あんまりピンと来ないっていうか…
I'm kind of drawing a blank.
Is that like hypocrisy?
偽善？　…みたいな
なんか それ必要？　…みたいな
It's like something you need, or what?
Education, huh?
教育か…　教育とは
うまいこと言ったもんだよ
If only it were as easy as it sounds.
Our job is to teach and raise students.
（国分）“教える”に“育てる”か
Take "raise" out of the equation,
and I would never have gotten involved...
“育”の字がなけりゃ
とっくに放り出してるぜ
in this whole issue.
こんなこと…
Snore, snore...
Wheeze...
（あかり）ひな！
Hina!
To Kawamoto Hinata
From Sakura Chiho
It's from Chiho!
ちほちゃんからだ
Hina, I'm sorry it's taken me so long to get back to you.
（ちほ）ひなちゃん
お返事が遅くなって
ごめんなさい
Right now, I'm studying with a teacher at a place called a "Heart Care Center."
（ちほ）私は今
“心のケアセンター”という所で
先生と一緒に勉強中です
ここは
周りが山と森で囲まれた—
It's a quiet, pretty area surrounded by mountains and forests.
静かで きれいな所です
センターの隣は牧場と農園で—
There's a ranch and farm next to the center.
They let me help out there sometimes.
今は そこで時々
お手伝いをさせてもらっています
この子は牧場で生まれた子ヤギです
メイちゃんといいます
This is a baby goat that was born on the ranch.
Her name is Mei.
The dog to my left is Hana.
隣は 犬のハナちゃん
They always come running over
to see me when I go to the ranch.
２人とも 牧場に行くと
私を見つけて 飛んできてくれます
They're the first friends I made here.
ここで 最初にできたお友達です
All of the people on the farm and ranch are very friendly.
牧場と農園の人たちも
とってもいい人ばかりです
So are the people who live nearby.
近所の人たちも
The other day, we made plum wine, plum syrup, and plum jam together.
この間は みんなで 梅酒と
梅シロップと梅ジャムを作りました
My mom helped too. It was lots of fun.
お母さんも一緒で楽しかった
My dad's office isn't too far from the center,
so he drops me off and picks me up every day.
単身赴任だった お父さんの会社も
車で少しの所で—
毎日 送り迎えしてくれます
I'm really happy I have more chances to talk to him now.
いっぱい話せるようになって
とても うれしいです
When I first came here, I couldn't get used to this new place, so I was really lonely.
ここに来たとき 最初は—
新しい場所に慣れなくて
とても寂しかった
But then Ms. Satou, my teacher at the center,
taught me the three steps to making a friend.
そんなとき
センターの佐藤(さとう)先生に—
お友達を作る３つのステップと
いうものを教わりました
You start by making friends with animals.
“まず最初は
動物のお友達を作りましょう”
After that, the next step is making friends with people who are older than you.
“それができたら
次は 年が上のお友達を”
And today...
（ちほ）そして 今日
For Ms. Satou
先生に—
Ms. Satou said, "Why don't we move on to the third step?"
“３つ目のステップに
進んでみましょうか”と—
言ってもらいました
The third step is making friends with
someone who's close to your own age.
３つ目のステップは
“年の近い友達を作る”です
私は それを聞いたとき…
When I heard that,
I thought about you, Hina.
ひなちゃんの顔を思い出しました
I really miss you.
とても…
とても会いたいと思いました
梅シロップが
おいしく出来上がったら—
When the plum syrup is just right, I'd like to drink some with you.
ひなちゃんと飲みたいです
I planted corn too.
トウモロコシも植えました
８月には実がなります
It'll be ready to pick by August.
I'd like to eat the corn with you.
一緒に食べたいです
Will you come and visit me during summer vacation?
（ちほ）
夏休み 遊びに来ませんか？
待っててもいい？　ちほより
Can I look forward to your visit?
From Chiho.
A Small Palm
In the Sun
（零(れい)）こんにちは
Hello!
（零）ンンッ…　失礼しま〜す…
Pardon me.
She's sleeping.
寝てる
Wants to go in,
but can't
*Unsure if it's okay to
enter a house where
a girl's sleeping
*Unsure if it's okay to
enter a house where
a girl's sleeping
Oomph...
（零）よっこらしょっと…
Sat down for now
I'm not sure why, but for the first time in a while,
何だろう？　久しぶりだ
she has this soft aura around her.
彼女の周りの空気が柔らかい
It's like she's faintly glowing.
なんか
ぼんやりと光っているような…
ずっと 見ていたいような…
Feels like I could look at her like this forever.
（ひなた）零ちゃん…
Rei...
零ちゃん
Rei.
Rei!
Apparently
nodded off
Wow! Summer tangerines!
（ひなた）
わあ 夏みかんだ！　こんなに
And there's so many!
My workshop mentor gave them to me.
（零）研究会で先輩にもらったんだ
いっぱい採れたから持ってけって
He picked a ton, so he told me to take them.
I can't believe I fell asleep on her doorstep.
いかん
つい つられて 寝てしまった
Oh, wow!
（零）おお すごい　こんなに…
This sure is...
…ていうか
えっ 全部？　島田(しまだ)さんは？
Wait, all of them?
What about you, Shimada?
It grew on your property, but you won't eat any?
せっかく なったのに
食べないんですか？
Nah, I have a feeling the acid in the tangerines would melt through my stomach lining.
（島田）いやぁ 夏みかんの酸で
胃壁が溶けそうな気がしてさ
There are no pesticides on them, so you can make jam and stuff.
農薬とかついてないから
ジャムとかにできるぞ
I can't, though.
俺は作れんけど…
Hahaha...
Jam?
Oh!
（零）あかりさん
Akari.
You're saving me money on groceries again!
（あかり）いやぁ
食費がまた浮いちゃう　ジャム作る
I'll make jam!
It smells good.
（ひなた）いい匂い　うれしいな
This'll be great.
Sis's marmalade is delicious.
お姉ちゃんのマーマレード
おいしいんだ
Just as I thought, she's faintly glowing.
やっぱり ぼうっと光ってる
なんでだろう？
I wonder why.
Kiriyama, actually...
（ひなた）桐山(きりやま)君　あのね…
It seems like it's over.
終わったみたい
Huh?
終わったんだと思う
I think it's over.
Probably.
多分…
（零）ああ そうか
I see.
So that's why...
これは その光か
she's glowing.
Cute, right?
かわいいでしょう？
We baked them yesterday at my classmate Kawashima's house.
昨日 同じクラスの川島(かわしま)さん家(ち)で
みんなで作ったの
We're in the same group.
同じ班なの
Kiuchi, Kobayashi, and Kudou are
in the group too, so five of us total.
木内(きうち)さんと小林(こばやし)さんと
工藤(くどう)さんと５人で
（木内）川本さん
Kawamoto.
（木内）あのね 今日 川島さん家で
クッキー作ろうって言ってて…
So, we're going to make cookies today at Kawashima's house.
（木内）一緒に来ない？
（ひなた）えっ？
Want to join us?
Huh?
えっと…
Um...
I'm sorry!
（川島）
ごめんなさい！　こ… 怖かったの
I-I was scared.
That's why I couldn't do anything.
（川島）
だから 何もできなかったの
Even if we apologize, we thought that...
私たち
謝っても もう許してなんか…
…もらえないかもしれないけど
you might not forgive us...
But I really wanted to apologize to you.
でも どうしても謝りたくって…
After that,
（ひなた）
それから 服を着替えて—
I changed clothes,
then met up with the girls at Kawashima's house.
もう一度
川島さんの家(うち)に集まって…
We baked tons of cookies together.
（ひなた）みんなで
たくさんのクッキーを焼いた
The cookies turned out hard and misshapen.
（ひなた）出来上がったクッキーは
不格好で堅くって…
ヒイッ…
なに これ　まずっ！
What is this? It's disgusting!
After I said that,
（ひなた）…て言ったら
みんなで笑いが 止まらなくなった
we couldn't stop laughing.
While we were laughing,
そして みんなで笑って—
we said, "Still, freshly-baked cookies are good,"
“でも 焼きたては
おいしいね”って—
and kept wolfing them down.
いくつも いくつも食べた
I wonder why.
なんでだろう？
Store-bought cookies taste much better,
買ったクッキーのほうが
ずっとずっと おいしいのに—
but I had such a good time and was so happy that they were delicious.
楽しくて おいしくて うれしくて
Did you know this, Kiriyama?
桐山君　知ってる？
When you put a cookie straight from the oven into your mouth, it sizzles.
焼きたてって 口に入れると
“ジュッ”っていうんだよ
I burned the inside of my mouth.
口ん中 ヤケドしちゃった　ほら！
Look!
（零）そう言って—
Saying that,
無邪気に
口を開けて見せる彼女の歯とか舌に
she innocently opened her mouth wide.
When I saw the sunlight on her teeth and tongue,
日が当たっているのを見て—
for some reason all sorts of feelings welled up inside me.
僕は なんだか
いろんなものが込み上げてきて—
I had a tightening sensation in my chest and felt like I was going to cry.
胸が苦しいような
泣きたいような気持ちになった
ひなちゃん ごめん
Hina, I'm sorry.
I...
僕は…
In the end, I couldn't help you at all.
結局 僕は何もできなかった
That's right.
（零）
そうだ　僕は あのとき ここで…
Even though I promised right here
that I would protect you.
君を守ると約束したのに
At all?
“何も”？
Kiriyama.
（ひなた）桐山君
あんなに… あんなに…
Even though...
you listened...
たくさん…
to me all those times?
話を聞いてくれたのに？
Even though you went to Kyoto to search for me?
京都まで捜しに来てくれたのに？
Even though you made me so happy?
私が あんなに うれしかったのに？
ええっ？　だって 結果的には…
After all, I wasn't able to...
（かみつく音）
いてっ！
Chomp
Ow!
Don't give me that!
（ひなた）
“だって”じゃない　ウウ…
What the?!
what
the?!
B-But I...
で… でも 僕は…
No buts!
“でも”じゃない！
ンンッ…　桐山君のバカ！
Kiriyama, you're an idiot!
（かみつく音）
（零）いたっ！
Chomp
Ouch!
Oh, that's right! Guess what!
（ひなた）そうだ！　あのね…
ちほちゃんから手紙が来たの
I got a letter from Chiho!
From Chiho?
（零）ちほちゃんから？　ホント？
Really?
And then, you know what?
でね　でね
During summer vacation, I'm definitely going to visit her!
私ね 夏休みになったら
会いに行くんだ　絶対
While telling me that, she pulled me by the hand as if
we were dancing and started walking at a steady pace.
（零）そう言って
踊るように僕の手を引いて—
彼女はグングンと歩きだす
And to this small heroine who never gave in, no matter how much she cried or suffered,
そして 僕は
どんなに泣いても 苦しくても—
決して意志を曲げなかった—
この小さな勇者に
心の中で もう一度…
I made another promise,
and a little oath of loyalty in my head.
小さく忠誠を誓った
In the Sun
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
Next Episode Preview
What is this?
Episode 36
（島田）なに？　これ
なに？　このポスター
What is this poster?
Why is the design so cool?
（柳原(やなぎはら)）デザイン
超カッコイイんですけど
It's my fault?
（島田）俺のせい？
Yes.
（零）はい
But for some reason,
it doesn't feel real to me.
でも なんだか
現実感が湧かなくって
Did you tell her that?
（林田(はやしだ)）
それ 彼女に言ったか？
It's easy to figure out.
分かるよ んなもん
I've been listening to
you this whole time.
ずっと
話聞いてきたんだからさ
Illustration: Watanabe Akio
Maybe I'll have Sis tell me how to make
marmalade so I can make it too!
（ひなた）お姉ちゃんに
教えてもらって—
私も マーマレード
作ってみよっかな